I'm thrilled to be here tonight
أنا سعيد لكوني هنا الليلة
to share with you something we've been working on
لكي اشارك معكم بعض العمل الذي نقوم به
for over two years,
ﻷكثر من سنتين
and it's in the area of additive manufacturing,
و عملي في مجال الصناعة بالأضافة
also known as 3D printing.
و أيضا معروفة بالطباعة ثلاثية اﻷبعاد
You see this object here.
هل ترون هذا الشيء
It looks fairly simple, but it's quite complex at the same time.
انه يبدو بسيطا للغاية. و لكنه في نفس الوقت معقد جدا
It's a set of concentric geodesic structures
انه مجموعة من الجيوديسيدات متحدة المركز
with linkages between each one.
بروابط بين كل منها.
In its context, it is not manufacturable by traditional manufacturing techniques.
بهذه الصورة، هو غير قابل للتصنيع باساليب الصناعة التقليدية
It has a symmetry such that you can't injection mold it.
انه متماثل بحيث لا يمكنك صبها بواسطة الحقن
You can't even manufacture it through milling.
و لا يمكنك حتى تصنيعه بواسطة التفريز
This is a job for a 3D printer,
هذه مهمة الطابعة ثلاثية اﻷبعاد
but most 3D printers would take between three and 10 hours to fabricate it,
لكن يستغرق تصنيعها من 3 الى 10 ساعات بأغلب الطابعات الثلاثية اﻷبعاد
and we're going to take the risk tonight to try to fabricate it onstage
و نحن سنخاطر لتصنيعها الليلة على المسرح
during this 10-minute talk.
خلال العشر دقائق مدة هذه المحادثة
Wish us luck.
تمنوا لنا الحظ
Now, 3D printing is actually a misnomer.
حسنا، الطباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد في الحقيقه تسمية غير دقيقة
It's actually 2D printing over and over again,
انها في الحقيقة طبقات من الطباعة ثنائية الابعاد بعضها فوق بعض
and it in fact uses the technologies associated with 2D printing.
و هي في الحقيقة تستخدم التكنولوجيا المصاحبة للطباعة ثنائية البعد
Think about inkjet printing where you lay down ink on a page to make letters,
فكروا بطابعة ورق حبريه و ما نفعله هو صب الحبر على الورق لتكوين الحروف
and then do that over and over again to build up a three-dimensional object.
قوموا بتكرار العمليه مرارا مع وضع الطبقات بعضها على بعض لبناء شكل جسم ثلاثي الأبعاد
In microelectronics, they use something
في الالكترونيات الدقيقه انهم يستخدمون شيء
called lithography to do the same sort of thing,
يسمى ليثوجرافي لفعل اشياء بنفس هذا الاسلوب
to make the transistors and integrated circuits
لتصنيع الترانزيستور و شرائح الدوائر المتكاملة
and build up a structure several times.
و لتصنيع جسم لعدة مرات
These are all 2D printing technologies.
هذه هي كل الاساليب التكنولوجية المستخدمة في الطباعه ثنائية اﻷبعاد
Now, I'm a chemist, a material scientist too,
حسنا، أنا كيميائي، كما أنني عالم في المواد
and my co-inventors are also material scientists,
كما أن شركائي المخترعين ايضا علماء مواد
one a chemist, one a physicist,
أحدهم كيميائي و الآخر فيزيائي
and we began to be interested in 3D printing.
و قد بدأنا الاهتمام بالطباعة ثلاثية اﻷبعاد
And very often, as you know, new ideas are often simple connections
و غالبا كما تعلمون فان الافكار الجديده غالبا علاقات بسيطة
between people with different experiences in different communities,
بأناس ذوي خبرات مختلفة و من مجتمعات مختلفة
and that's our story.
و هذه هي قصتنا
Now, we were inspired
حسنا، لقد ألهمنا
by the "Terminator 2" scene for T-1000,
مشهد من فيلم ( 2 terminator) ل T-1000
and we thought, why couldn't a 3D printer operate in this fashion,
و فكرنا لماذا لا يمكن لطابعة ثلاثية اﻷبعاد أن تعمل بهذه الطريقة
where you have an object arise out of a puddle
حيث يكون لديك جسم يبرز من خلال عجين
in essentially real time
في وقت آني
with essentially no waste
و بدون مخلّفات
to make a great object?
لصنع أشياء عظيمة ؟
Okay, just like the movies.
حسنا تماما مثل الأفلام
And could we be inspired by Hollywood
و هل يمكن ان تلهمنا هوليوود
and come up with ways to actually try to get this to work?
و نصل لطريقه لتنفيذ هذا العمل؟
And that was our challenge.
و كان هذا هو تحدينا
And our approach would be, if we could do this,
و كانت مقاربتنا أننا لو استطعنا عمل هذا
then we could fundamentally address the three issues holding back 3D printing
اذن فيمكننا وضع الاعتبارات الثلاثة الرئيسيه التي تمنع الطباعه ثلاثية الأبعاد
from being a manufacturing process.
من أن تصبح عملية صناعية
One, 3D printing takes forever.
أولا، الطباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد تأخذ وقتا طويلا
There are mushrooms that grow faster than 3D printed parts. (Laughter)
فهناك عش غراب ينمو أسرع من أجزاء مطبوعة بثلاثية الأبعاد. (ضحك)
The layer by layer process
استخدام عمليه التصنيع طبقة فوق طبقة
leads to defects in mechanical properties,
تقود الى تشوه في الخواص الميكانيكية
and if we could grow continuously, we could eliminate those defects.
و لو أستطعنا أن ننتج الأجزاء بشكل مستمر فأنه يمكننا تلافي هذه التشوهات
And in fact, if we could grow really fast, we could also start using materials
و لو استطعنا أن ننتجها حقا بسرعة ، فانه يمكننا البدء باستخدام مواد
that are self-curing, and we could have amazing properties.
ذاتية المعالجة، و عليه يمكننا الحصول على خصائص مذهله.
So if we could pull this off, imitate Hollywood,
لذلك لو استطعنا سحب هذا الشئ خارجا، بشكل يحاكي هوليوود،
we could in fact address 3D manufacturing.
فأنه يمكننا في الحقيقه نباشر التصنيع ثلاثي الأبعاد.
Our approach is to use some standard knowledge
طريقتنا هي استخدام بعض المعرفة الأولية
in polymer chemistry
في كيمياء البوليمرات
to harness light and oxygen to grow parts continuously.
لجمع الضوء مع الاكسجين لانتاج أشياء بشكل مستمر.
Light and oxygen work in different ways.
الضوء و الأكسجين يعملان بطريقتين مختلفتين.
Light can take a resin and convert it to a solid,
الضوء يستطيع أن يأخذ مادة راتنجية (صمغية) و يحولها لماده صلبة،
can convert a liquid to a solid.
و يستطيع تحويل سائل الى صلب،
Oxygen inhibits that process.
و الأكسجين يثبط هذه العملية.
So light and oxygen are polar opposites from one another
لذلك فالضوء و الأكسجين على طرفي نقيض.
from a chemical point of view,
من وجهه نظر الكيمياء،
and if we can control spatially the light and oxygen,
و لو استطعنا التحكم مكانيا في الضوء و اﻷكسجين،
we could control this process.
فانه يمكننا التحكم في هذه العميله.
And we refer to this as CLIP. [Continuous Liquid Interface Production.]
و نحن نشير الى هذا ب .CLIP ( الانتاج المستمر لسطح بيني سائل).
It has three functional components.
و هو يحتوي على ثلاث مكونات وظيفية.
One, it has a reservoir that holds the puddle,
أولا، يحتوى على وعلء للعجين،
just like the T-1000.
تماما مثل T-1000.
At the bottom of the reservoir is a special window.
في قاع هذا الوعاء توجد نافذة خاصة.
I'll come back to that.
و سأعود اليها لاحقا.
In addition, it has a stage that will lower into the puddle
بالاضافة الى ذلك، فهي تحتوي على درجه تنخفض في هذا العجين
and pull the object out of the liquid.
و تسحب الجسم خارج السائل.
The third component is a digital light projection system
أما المكون الثالث فهو نظام اسقاط ضوئي رقمي
underneath the reservoir,
تحت الخزان،
illuminating with light in the ultraviolet region.
يتوهج بضوء فوق بنفسجي.
Now, the key is that this window in the bottom of this reservoir,
و الآن، أهم جزء وهو النافذة الموجودة أسفل الوعاء،
it's a composite, it's a very special window.
انها مركبه، انها نافذة خاصة جدا.
It's not only transparent to light but it's permeable to oxygen.
انها ليست فقط شفافه لعبور الضوء و لكنها نافذه أيضا للأكسجين.
It's got characteristics like a contact lens.
ان لها خصائص مثل عدسات النظر.
So we can see how the process works.
اذن نستطيع رؤيه كيف تعمل هذه الطريقة
You can start to see that as you lower a stage in there,
تستطيعون الآن رؤيه أنه مع خفض الدرجه هناك
in a traditional process, with an oxygen-impermeable window,
في عمليه تقليدية، مع نافذه منفذه للأكسجين،
you make a two-dimensional pattern
يمكنكم عمل شكل ثنائي اﻷبعاد
and you end up gluing that onto the window with a traditional window,
و تنتهون بلصق هذا على النافذه بنافذه عادية
and so in order to introduce the next layer, you have to separate it,
و هكذا لانتاج الطبقه التالية، يجب عليكم فصلها،
introduce new resin, reposition it,
انتاج الراتينج الجديد، أعيدوها،
and do this process over and over again.
و كرروا هذه العمليه مرات و مرات.
But with our very special window,
و لكم باستخدام نافذه خاصه جدا،
what we're able to do is, with oxygen coming through the bottom
ما يمكننا فعله، مع الأكسجين القادم من القاع
as light hits it,
عندما يقع عليه الضوء،
that oxygen inhibits the reaction,
فان الأكسجين يثبط التفاعل،
and we form a dead zone.
و نكون منطقة ميتة.
This dead zone is on the order of tens of microns thick,
هذه المنطقة الميتة سُمكها عدة عشرات من الميكرون متر.
so that's two or three diameters of a red blood cell,
هذا حوالي مرتان الى ثلاث أضعاف قطر كرات الدم الحمراء،
right at the window interface that remains a liquid,
تماما عند سطح النافذه يبقى العجسن سائلا،
and we pull this object up,
و نحن نسحب هذا الجسم لأعلى،
and as we talked about in a Science paper,
و كما تحدثنا عمه في بحث علمي،
as we change the oxygen content, we can change the dead zone thickness.
كلما استطعنا تغيير كميه الأكسجين، كلما استطعنا تغيير سُمك الطبقة الميتة.
And so we have a number of key variables that we control: oxygen content,
اذن لدينا عدة متغيرات رئيسيه نستطيع التحكم بها: كميه اﻷكسجين،
the light, the light intensity, the dose to cure,
الضوء، شده الضوء، الجرعة المعالجه،
the viscosity, the geometry,
اللزوجه، الشكل الهندسي،
and we use very sophisticated software to control this process.
و نستخدم برنامج معقد جدا للتحكم في هذه العملية.
The result is pretty staggering.
النتيجه مذهله جدا.
It's 25 to 100 times faster than traditional 3D printers,
انها أسرع ب 25 الى 100 مرة من الطابعات ثلاثيه اﻷبعاد التقليدية،
which is game-changing.
و هذا تغيير في قواعد اللعبه.
In addition, as our ability to deliver liquid to that interface,
بالاضافه الى ذلك. كلما زادت قدرتنا على دفع السائل للمنطقه الفاصلة،
we can go 1,000 times faster I believe,
نستطيع الوصول الى 1000 مرة أسرع حسبما أعتقد،
and that in fact opens up the opportunity for generating a lot of heat,
و هذا في الحقيقه يعطي فرصة لانتاج كميه كبيره من الحرارة،
and as a chemical engineer, I get very excited at heat transfer
و ﻷنني مهندس كيميائي فاني مهتم جدا بانتقال الحراره
and the idea that we might one day have water-cooled 3D printers,
و الفكره أنه من المحتمل أن نمتلك طابعه ثلاثية اﻷبعاد تبرد بالماء يوم ما،
because they're going so fast.
لأنها سوف تعمل بشكل سريع جدا.
In addition, because we're growing things, we eliminate the layers,
بالاضافه الى ذلك، و ﻷننا ننتج أجسام فنحن نلغي الفواصل الطبقية،
and the parts are monolithic.
لتصبح اﻷجزاء متجانسه و متحدة
You don't see the surface structure.
فأنتم لا تستطيعون رؤيه اﻷسطح.
You have molecularly smooth surfaces.
فلديكم أسطح متجانسه على مستوى الجزيئات.
And the mechanical properties of most parts made in a 3D printer
و الخصائص الميكانيكيه لأغلب الأجزاء المصنوعة بالطابعه ثلاثية اﻷبعاد
are notorious for having properties that depend on the orientation
موسومة بأن خصائصها تعتمد على الاتجاه
with which how you printed it, because of the layer-like structure.
الذي تقوم بطباعتها عليه، بفعل البناء الطبقي.
But when you grow objects like this,
و لكن عند انتاج اجزاء بهذه الطريقة،
the properties are invariant with the print direction.
فان الخصائص لا تعتمد على اتجاه الطباعة.
which is very different than traditional 3D manufacturing.
المختلف كليا عن الطباعه ثلاثية اﻷبعاد التقليدية.
In addition, we're able to throw
اضافة، نحن نستطيع الاستغناء
the entire polymer chemistry textbook at this,
عن كتاب كيمياء البوليمرات،
and we're able to design chemistries that can give rise to the properties
و نستطيع تصميم طرق كيميائية تستطيع تحسين الخواص
you really want in a 3D-printed object.
التي تريدها فعلا للطباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
There it is. That's great.
هذه هي. هذا عظيم.
You always take the risk that something like this won't work onstage, right?
أنت دائما تخاطر بأن شيء كهذا قد لا يعمل على المسرح، صحيح؟
But we can have materials with great mechanical properties.
و لكننا نستطيع الحصول على مواد بخصائص ميكانيكية عظيمة.
For the first time, we can have elastomers
للمره اﻷولى، من الممكن ان يكون لدينا لدائن
that are high elasticity or high dampening.
مرنة جدا أو ماصّة جيدة للصدمات.
Think about vibration control or great sneakers, for example.
فكروا بالتحكم في الاهتزازات أو أحذية رياضيه عظيمة، على سبيل المثال.
We can make materials that have incredible strength,
من الممكن تصنيع مواد لها صلابة هائلة،
high strength-to-weight ratio, really strong materials,
صلابة عالية لكل وحده وزن، مواد قوية حقا،
really great elastomers,
لدائن عظيمة حقا،
so throw that in the audience there.
اذن أقذف هذا للمستمعين هناك.
So great material properties.
خواص عظيمة للمواد.
And so the opportunity now, if you actually make a part
و كذلك الفرصه الآن، لو قمنا تصنيع جسم
that has the properties to be a final part,
له خصائص تصلح لمنتج نهائي،
and you do it in game-changing speeds,
و أنت تفعل ذلك بسرعات مختلفة،
you can actually transform manufacturing.
يمكنك فعلا تغيير التصنيع.
Right now, in manufacturing, what happens is,
حاليا، في التصنيع، ما يحدث هو،
the so-called digital thread in digital manufacturing.
ما يسمى بالخيط الرقمي في الصناعة الرقمية.
We go from a CAD drawing, a design, to a prototype to manufacturing.
فنحن نستطيع البدء من رسم بالكومبيوتر، تصميم نموذج للتصنيع.
Often, the digital thread is broken right at prototype,
عادة تنقطع الخيوط عند مرحله النمذجة،
because you can't go all the way to manufacturing
لأنك لا تستطيع المرور بكل الطريق نحو التصنيع
because most parts don't have the properties to be a final part.
ﻷن معظم الشياء لا تملك الخصائص التي تمكنها من جعلها منتج نهائي.
We now can connect the digital thread
يمكننا الآن ربط الخيوط الرقمية
all the way from design to prototyping to manufacturing,
على طول الطريق من التصميم الى النمذجة الى التصنيع.
and that opportunity really opens up all sorts of things,
و هذه الفرصة حقا تفتح المجال لكل انواع الأشياء،
from better fuel-efficient cars dealing with great lattice properties
من سيارات أكفأ في استخدام الوقود تتعامل مع خصائص شعرية عظيمة
with high strength-to-weight ratio,
بمقدار عالي من نسبة القوة الى الوزن،
new turbine blades, all sorts of wonderful things.
ريش محركات جديدة، كل اﻷشياء الرائعه.
Think about if you need a stent in an emergency situation,
فكروا لو أنكم تحتاجون دعامة في موقف طارئ،
instead of the doctor pulling off a stent out of the shelf
فبدلا من أن يقوم الطبيب بأخة دعامة من على الرف
that was just standard sizes,
حيث هناك أحجام قياسية فقط،
having a stent that's designed for you, for your own anatomy
ستحصل على دعامه ممصمة لك، طبقا لتشريح جسدك
with your own tributaries,
باستخدام أجزاء من جسدك،
printed in an emergency situation in real time out of the properties
الطباعة في المواقف الطارئة في وقت آني
such that the stent could go away after 18 months: really-game changing.
و يمكن لهذه الدعامة أن تخرج بعد 18 شهرا فعلا تغيير في قواعد اللعبة.
Or digital dentistry, and making these kinds of structures
أو في طب اﻷسنان الرقمي هذا النوع من التركيبات
even while you're in the dentist chair.
حتى أثناء جلوسك على كرسي طبيب اﻷسنان.
And look at the structures that my students are making
و تنظر الى التركيبات التي قد يصنعها طلابي
at the University of North Carolina.
في جامعة كارولينا الشمالية.
These are amazing microscale structures.
هذه تركيبات دقيقة رائعة.
You know, the world is really good at nano-fabrication.
تعلمون، العالم حقا جيد التصنيع الدقيق جدا (النانو).
Moore's Law has driven things from 10 microns and below.
قانون مور أثبت أشياء من 10 ميكرون و أقل.
We're really good at that,
حقا نحن جيدين في هذا،
but it's actually very hard to make things from 10 microns to 1,000 microns,
و لكن في الواقع فأنه من الصعب جدا صنع أشياء من 10 الى 1000 ميكرون،
the mesoscale.
في مقياس الميزو.
And subtractive techniques from the silicon industry
و طرق الكشط من صناعة السيليكون
can't do that very well.
لا تستطيع عمل هذا بشكل جيد.
They can't etch wafers that well.
انها لا تستطيع حفر الرقائق جيدا.
But this process is so gentle,
و لكن هذه الطريقة
we can grow these objects up from the bottom
نستطيع انبات هذه الأجزاء من القاع الى اعلى
using additive manufacturing
باستخدام الصناعة بالاضافة.
and make amazing things in tens of seconds,
و صنع اشياء مذهلة في عشرات الثواني،
opening up new sensor technologies,
تفتح عصرا جديدا في تكنولوجيا المستشعرات،
new drug delivery techniques,
طرق جديده لتوصيل اﻷدوية،
new lab-on-a-chip applications, really game-changing stuff.
تطبيقات جديده لمعمل على شريحة، حقا تغيير في قواعد اللعبة.
So the opportunity of making a part in real time
لذلك فان فرصة صناعة أجزاء في وقت آني
that has the properties to be a final part
و لديها خصائص منتج نهائي
really opens up 3D manufacturing,
تفتح الطريق حقا للصناعه ثلاثية البعد،
and for us, this is very exciting, because this really is owning
و بالنسبه لنا، فان هذا مثير جدا لأنه حقا يحتوي على
the intersection between hardware, software and molecular science,
التداخل بين العتاد ، و البرمجيات و علم الجزيئات
and I can't wait to see what designers and engineers around the world
و أنا لا استطيع الانتظار ﻷرى المصممين و المهندسين حول العالم
are going to be able to do with this great tool.
على وشك القدره على انجاز أعمالهم بهذه الأداة.
Thanks for listening.
شكرا لاستماعكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)